Preliminary Inventory of the Marek Łatyński papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Marek Łatyński papers
1958-2002
2017C3
Hoover Institution Archives
16 manuscript boxes (6.7 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, memoranda, reports, broadcast transcripts, and printed matter relating to radio broadcasting to Poland, and to Polish-Swiss relations.
Łatyński, Marek.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2016.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collections
Andrzej Czechowicz papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Zdzisław Najder papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
Marek Łatyński, a Polish journalist, was born in Warsaw in 1930 into a middle-class family. Much of his childhood and youth coincided with periods of Nazi and Stalinist terror in Poland. During the German occupation of the country, he attended classes in an underground gymnasium. After the war, the communists imprisoned his father for six years on charges of "economic sabotage." Łatyński’s university studies were in English language and literature at the universities of Cracow and Warsaw. He was also very interested in twentieth-century Polish history but had to study it on his own, as this was a subject under the rigid control of the Communist Party. Although still a student, Łatyński found employment in the Polish Radio’s foreign-language programming. He worked there until his defection from the Polish People’s Republic in 1967.
During a few months’ stay in Paris, Łatyński was noticed by two key Polish émigré leaders, Jerzy Giedroyc, the Paris publisher, and Jan Nowak-Jezioranski, the director of the Polish service of Radio Free Europe (RFE). Nowak offered Łatyński a job with RFE in Munich. His association with RFE, first in charge of daily news and later as director of the Polish service, lasted until the end of 1989, with a two-year hiatus in the 1980s when he served as Voice of America’s commentator on East Central Europe in Washington, D.C.
Łatyński returned to Munich as director of RFE’s Polish broadcast service in 1987. His tenure, from March 1987 through November 1989, coincided with the momentous changes taking place in Poland and within the Soviet bloc, led by the last Soviet Communist Party general secretary, Mikhail Gorbachev. In January 1988, the communists stopped jamming RFE programming and the Munich radio greatly increased its daily presence in Poland. Live telephone interviews with Solidarity opposition leaders and prominent cultural and religious figures, combined with in-depth uncensored international and domestic news, helped solidify national consensus for a peaceful political change. Under Łatyński’s direction, Radio Free Europe Polish broadcasting became an important medium for the anticommunist opposition during the Round Table Talks with the communist regime and the semi-free elections of June 1989, which opened the way for a democratic Poland. In July 1989, Łatyński made his first trip to his homeland in more than two decades, as a member of George H. Bush’s press entourage during the president’s official visit to Poland.
Łatyński briefly worked as the Paris commentator for the Polish radio and, from 1991 to 1994, served as Poland’s ambassador to Switzerland. He also continued to write and publish, first his RFE memoirs, titled The English Garden (the Munich street address of RFE), and later a greatly expanded and revised edition of his study on Stalinist terror in Poland of the 1940s and early 1950s. Łatyński died in Warsaw in 2003.
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Marek Łatyński consist of his RFE papers, the archives connected with his ambassadorial tenure in Bern, and his historical manuscripts. Materials include correspondence, writings, memoranda, reports, broadcast transcripts, and printed matter.
Radio Free Europe.; Radio broadcasting--Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--Switzerland.; Switzerland--Foreign relations--Poland.
- Radio Wolna Europa (RWE) - opracowania z okresu wczesnego, 1958 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- RWE - audycje z pierwszych lat, 1968-1973 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- RWE - oceny i opinie amerykanskie, 1968-1985 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- RWE - wybrane komentarze, 1973-1985 (Box-folder 1: 4)
- RWE - Jan Nowak-Jezioranski, 1975-1993 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Komentarze, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Materialy rozne, undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
- RWE - oceny programu z zewnatrz, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 2: 3)
- Wywiady z Kisielewskim i Czapskim, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- RWE i Kultura Giedroyca, 1975-1979 (Box-folder 3: 1)
- Teksty o Dwudziestoleciu i o wojsku, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 3: 2)
- Audycje z Okresu Paryskiego, 1990 (Box-folder 3: 3)
- RWE w mediach zachodnich, undated (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Korespondencja z ludzmi z zewnatrz, 1983-1989 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- RWE - memoranda i korespondencja wewnetrzna, 1987-1990 (Box-folder 4: 1)
- RWE w prasie krajowej po 1989 (Box-folder 4: 2)
- Pobyt w Warszawie i wywiad w Tygodniku Powszechnym, 1989 (Box-folder 4: 3)
- RWE - krajowi uczestnicy audycji, 1987 (Box-folder 4: 4)
- RWE i ksiazka, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
- RWE - lata po odejsciu, undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
- Michalowski, undated (Box-folder 5: 1)
- Najder, undated (Box-folder 5: 2)
- Wlodzimierz Odojewski - korespondencja, undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
- RWE - sprawy personalne, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 5: 4)
- Zygmunt Stankiewicz, undated (Box-folder 5: 5)
- Alina Grabowska, listy, komentarze, artykuly, undated (Box-folder 5: 6)
- Krzysztof Skubiszewski, polityka polska, undated (Box-folder 5: 7)
- Pawel Zaremba, wspomnienia, korespondencja z Giedroyciem, 1979-1981 (Box-folder 5: 8)
- Czapski, Wozniakowski, 1988-1992 (Box-folder 5: 9)
- RWE - memoranda i korespondencja wewnetrzna, 1968-1985 (Box-folder 6: 1)
- RWE - audycje z okresu paryskiego (sierpien-pazdziernik), 1990 (Box-folder 6: 2)
- RWE w mediach krajowych, 1981-1989 (Box-folder 6: 3)
- RWE - sprawy personalne, 1968-1990 (Box-folder 6: 4)
- RWE - sprawa Urbana, 1988 (Box-folder 6: 5)
- RWE - wyjatki z ksiazek autorow amerykanskich, undated (Box-folder 7: 1)
- RWE - wystapienia publiczne, 1977-1990 (Box-folder 7: 2)
- RWE - audycje z okresu paryskiego (czerwiec-lipiec), 1990 (Box-folder 7: 3)
- RWE - listy - przyjscie Z. Najdera jako dyrektora, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 7: 4)
- RWE - rozne publikacje radiowe, 1963-1989 (Box-folder 7: 5)
- RWE - fraszki Jacka Kaczmarskiego, undated (Box-folder 7: 6)
- Berno, wycinki prasowe, listy, zaproszenia (lipiec), 1991 (Box-folder 8: 1)
- Berno, wycinki, korespondencja, artykuly ( sierpien-pazdziernik), 1991 (Box-folder 8: 2)
- Berno, korespondencja, wycinki prasowe (listopad-grudzien), 1991 (Box-folder 8: 3)
- Szwajcaria, Berno, korespondencja, zaproszenia, artykuly, 1992 (Box-folder 9: 1)
- Berno, wycinki prasowe, 1992 (Box-folder 9: 2)
- Berno, korespondencja, wycinki prasowe, 1992 (Box-folder 9: 3)
- Berno, wycinki, dokumenty, listy, 1993 (Box-folder 10: 1)
- Szwajcaria i sprawy polsko-szwajcarskie, undated (Box-folder 10: 2)
- Szwajcaria, artykuly, wycinki prasowe, undated (Box-folder 10: 3)
- Berno, Grande Societe, undated (Box-folder 10: 4)
- Berno, MSZ, wycinki prasowe, 1994-1998 (Box-folder 10: 5)
- Szwajcaria, zaproszenia, korespondencja, 1993 (Box-folder 11: 1)
- Sprawozdanie kierownika przedstawicielstwa dypolomatycznego, 1994 (Box-folder 11: 2)
- Dokumentacja przyjec prezydenckich i spotkan z Polonia, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 11: 3)
- Berno, pisma, artykuly, wycinki, korespondencja, 1993 (Box-folder 11: 4)
- Berno, notatki, korespondencja (wrzesien-pazdziernik), 1994 (Box-folder 12: 1)
- Berno, korespondencja, wycinki prasowe, artykuly, 1994 (Box-folder 12: 2)
- Berno, korespondencja, artykuly, wycinki prasowe (maj-sierpien), 1994 (Box-folder 12: 3)
- Listy, recenzje z ksiazki, zyciorys, projekt testamentu, 1998-2002 (Box-folder 13: 1)
- Sprawy w toku, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 13: 2)
- Narada w Warszawie, 1994 (Box-folder 13: 3)
- Listy gratulacyjne, nominacje, undated (Box-folder 13: 4)
- CIA i wywiad, wycinki prasowe, 1995-2003 (Box-folder 13: 5)
- Niezalezne publikacje polskie, 1979 (Box-folder 13: 6)
- Echa przerwanego wydania ksiazki, Nie pasc na kolana, 1985 (Box-folder 13: 7)
- Nie pasc na kolana, rozne materialy, 2002 (Box-folder 13: 8)
- Nie pasc na kolana, pozostalosci, korespondencja, etc., 1976-1982 (Box-folder 13: 9)
- PRL, materialy do ksiazki, undated (Box-folder 14: 1)
- PRL, dodatki do ksiazki, pozostalosci, undated (Box-folder 14: 2)
- Ogrod angielski, recenzje i inne reakcje, undated (Box-folder 14: 3)
- Nie pasc na kolana - maszynopis, pierwsza wersja poprawiona, undated (Box-folder 15: 1)
- Bibliografia do ksiazki, Nie pasc na kolana, undated (Box-folder 15: 2)
- "Wariacje na temat Jaruzelskiego,", undated (Box-folder 15: 3)
- Trzy pudelka z haslami do Indexu ksiazki Nie pasc na kolana, undated (Box 16)